<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-25T23:04:57-07:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">EB1 greecard deepdive</title><link href="/2020/02/25/EB1-deepdive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EB1 greecard deepdive" /><published>2020-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2020/02/25/EB1-deepdive</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/02/25/EB1-deepdive.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often refered to as the “extraordinary talent greencard” or “Employment-based, first preference”, the EB1 greencard is fast, and does not require employer sponsorship. As a result, it is also the most effortful to get, due to the high bar one needs to meet. This category is most suitable for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionally accomplished Indian or Chinese national, who might otherwise have to wait up to 10 years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any professionally accomplished person who wants to avoid being tied to a sponsoring employer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;eligibility-criteria&quot;&gt;Eligibility criteria&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to qualify for an EB1 greencard, applicants must satisfy at least three of the following ten criteria. Though this list might seem daunting, most moderately successful and well-connected professional can reasonably build up the evidence given enough time and will. They should expect to work on the order of a few hundred hours, assuming they don’t clearly meet any already. It is also possible, though rare, to instead demonstrate a single major international achievement on the magnitude of a Nobel prize, Fields medal, Oscar, Grammy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence of receipt of lesser nationally or internationally recognized prizes or awards for excellence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence of your membership in associations in the field which demand outstanding achievement of their members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence of published material about you in professional or major trade publications or other major media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence that you have been asked to judge the work of others, either individually or on a panel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence of your original scientific, scholarly, artistic, athletic, or business-related contributions of major significance to the field&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence of your authorship of scholarly articles in professional or major trade publications or other major media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence that your work has been displayed at artistic exhibitions or showcases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence of your performance of a leading or critical role in distinguished organizations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence that you command a high salary or other significantly high remuneration in relation to others in the field&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence of your commercial successes in the performing arts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each of these criteria, applicants use a combination of letters from authoritative figures and documentation to prove their eligibility. An adjudicator at USCIS evaluates the evidences, and issue either a pass, a request for evidence (RFE for short), or a denial (rare). The most common outcome is an RFE, where specific additional detail will be demanded from the applicant. Successfully meeting this request results in a pass. Failure results in a denial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, we’ll go over some examples cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;eligibility-example&quot;&gt;Eligibility example&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This applicant is a product designer for a tech company with a few thousand employees in San Francisco. Previously, they worked at an agency providing design services to well-known tech giants. They chose the following five criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-that-you-have-been-asked-to-judge-the-work-of-others-either-individually-or-on-a-panel&quot;&gt;Evidence that you have been asked to judge the work of others, either individually or on a panel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The applicant judged five university hackathons. Two hackathon organizers issued letters detailing the merits on which the applicant was selected as a judge, as well as a list of other judges, which included executives of well-known companies, professors, and public figures. Evidence also included screenshots of various events showing the full list of judges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcome: The adjudicator accepted this criterion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-of-your-original-scientific-scholarly-artistic-athletic-or-business-related-contributions-of-major-significance-to-the-field&quot;&gt;Evidence of your original scientific, scholarly, artistic, athletic, or business-related contributions of major significance to the field&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The applicant created a free software plugin that is popular within their field, and used by teams at well-known companies. The package included install statistics (more than 100k times), and a letter from the CEO of the company that makes the software for which the plugin was written, speaking to its importance. Screenshots from blogs discussing and featuring the plugin were also submitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcome: This criterion received an RFE requesting proof of the plugin’s significance. In response, the applicant submitted a clarifying letter from the same CEO with additonal statistics, as well as six letters from designers at well-known companies attesting to their use of the plugin and its impact. [insert outcome]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-of-your-authorship-of-scholarly-articles-in-professional-or-major-trade-publications-or-other-major-media&quot;&gt;Evidence of your authorship of scholarly articles in professional or major trade publications or other major media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The applicant spoke at a mix of podcast, local, and online events, both individually and as part of a panel. Screenshots of all the event websites were provided along with a letter from a professor of design stating how in this field, speaking at events is considered to be major media on the same level as journal publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcome: This criterion received an RFE requesting (?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-of-your-performance-of-a-leading-or-critical-role-in-distinguished-organizations&quot;&gt;Evidence of your performance of a leading or critical role in distinguished organizations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The applicant played critical roles in several major projects for his current employer, as well as his past one. Evidence incliudes: a letter from the CEO of his current company, letters from a product manager and design executive from clients of his previous explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcome: his criterion received an RFE requesting proof that the impact of the applicant’s role on the whole company and how it was beyond the scope of his normal work. The applicant supplied additional letters from senior executives addressing these questions. The applicant also challenged the necessity to demonstrate the criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evidence-that-you-command-a-high-salary-or-other-significantly-high-remuneration-in-relation-to-others-in-the-field&quot;&gt;Evidence that you command a high salary or other significantly high remuneration in relation to others in the field&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The applicant makes $230k a year, which is x% above the median for designers in the united states, demonstrated through sceenshots of salary data from glassdoor (?) and the applicant’s paystubs (?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcome: This criterion received an RFE for the applicant’s W2s. [insert outcome here]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-supporting-letters&quot;&gt;Get supporting letters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The applicant builds evidence and gets support letter demonstrating how they meet at least three of the ten EB1 criteria&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically takes: 2–4 months
Outcome: Applicant has strong evidence and support letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;submit-application-i-140&quot;&gt;Submit application (I-140)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence and supporting letters are mailed into USCIS, along with a filled out form I-140. This is the official greencard application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approval time: 3-6 months(?). Applicants can pay $1,500 for a 15 day response. This is called premium processing.
Outcome: Greencard application is either accepted, RFE’ed or rejected&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;respond-to-rfe-optional&quot;&gt;Respond to RFE (optional)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your application receives a request for evidence, you have three months (?) to brind additional document and/or objections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approval time: (?). 15 days if premium processing was purchased.
Outcome: Greencard application is either accepted or rejected&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;submit-adjustmnet-of-status-i-485&quot;&gt;Submit adjustmnet of status (I-485)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an application is accepted and if the applicant’s country’s date of filing (?) is current, the applicant can now file a request to change their status to a permanent resident via form I-485.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the green card faster, applicants can file the I-485 before their I-140 is accepted, with the risk of wasting money and effort should the latter be rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approval time: Depends on which USCIS service center you applied with
Outcome: Receive greencard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apply-for-travel-document-and-employment-authorization-i-131-and-i-765&quot;&gt;Apply for travel document and employment authorization (I-131 and I-765)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it can take a long time for an ajustment of status to get approved, people usually concurrently apply for travel docuemnt and employment authorization at the same time. These documents are faster to get, and when combined together, provide almost all the benefits of holding a greencard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approval time: Depends on which USCIS service center you applied with
Outcome: Be able to travel freely and work for whoever you want&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;advice&quot;&gt;Advice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generally it is better to put on a strong showing for fewer (typically four or five) criteria, than trying to do more but less well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have a previously accepted I-140 from a lower preference (EB2 or EB3), you can use that date to accelerate your EB1 if your country is not current.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It really helps to have access to famous people: senior executives, well-known professionals in your field, professors, public figures, etc. Cultivate these relationships early.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you don’t already clearly meet these criteria, plan for one to two years to go meet them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your letters on official letterhead, even if it’s not technically required. It can be a cause of RFE. In a pinch a “personal” letterhead could do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If your EB1 is approved, this means you’re almost guaranteed to also get approved for the O1 visa, which can be convenient if you need to work in the US while your greencard is processing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For people who are very likely to agree to signing a lettr, it is better to pre-write the lettter for them before you even ask if they want to do it. This way, you can immediately give them something to sign once they agree, saving yourself the back and forth from your lead going cold while your legal team works on the letter. You’ll be getting a lot of letters, so this adds up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On non-immigrant visas like the TN, it is inadvisable to leave the country from the day you submit your application until you get your travel authorization, even if your application is accepted. This could last anywhere from 6–8 months. You should plan ahead for this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The country of the greencard applicant is not based on their citizenship, but place of birth. A British citizen born in India is Indian from this perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spouses also get a greencard if you file together (?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When challenging an RFE, it is best to also respond to the request, even if unreasonable, as a show of good faith.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">TL;DR Often refered to as the “extraordinary talent greencard” or “Employment-based, first preference”, the EB1 greencard is fast, and does not require employer sponsorship. As a result, it is also the most effortful to get, due to the high bar one needs to meet. This category is most suitable for: Professionally accomplished Indian or Chinese national, who might otherwise have to wait up to 10 years. Any professionally accomplished person who wants to avoid being tied to a sponsoring employer Eligibility criteria In order to qualify for an EB1 greencard, applicants must satisfy at least three of the following ten criteria. Though this list might seem daunting, most moderately successful and well-connected professional can reasonably build up the evidence given enough time and will. They should expect to work on the order of a few hundred hours, assuming they don’t clearly meet any already. It is also possible, though rare, to instead demonstrate a single major international achievement on the magnitude of a Nobel prize, Fields medal, Oscar, Grammy, etc. Evidence of receipt of lesser nationally or internationally recognized prizes or awards for excellence Evidence of your membership in associations in the field which demand outstanding achievement of their members Evidence of published material about you in professional or major trade publications or other major media Evidence that you have been asked to judge the work of others, either individually or on a panel Evidence of your original scientific, scholarly, artistic, athletic, or business-related contributions of major significance to the field Evidence of your authorship of scholarly articles in professional or major trade publications or other major media Evidence that your work has been displayed at artistic exhibitions or showcases Evidence of your performance of a leading or critical role in distinguished organizations Evidence that you command a high salary or other significantly high remuneration in relation to others in the field Evidence of your commercial successes in the performing arts For each of these criteria, applicants use a combination of letters from authoritative figures and documentation to prove their eligibility. An adjudicator at USCIS evaluates the evidences, and issue either a pass, a request for evidence (RFE for short), or a denial (rare). The most common outcome is an RFE, where specific additional detail will be demanded from the applicant. Successfully meeting this request results in a pass. Failure results in a denial. Below, we’ll go over some examples cases. Eligibility example This applicant is a product designer for a tech company with a few thousand employees in San Francisco. Previously, they worked at an agency providing design services to well-known tech giants. They chose the following five criteria: Evidence that you have been asked to judge the work of others, either individually or on a panel The applicant judged five university hackathons. Two hackathon organizers issued letters detailing the merits on which the applicant was selected as a judge, as well as a list of other judges, which included executives of well-known companies, professors, and public figures. Evidence also included screenshots of various events showing the full list of judges. Outcome: The adjudicator accepted this criterion. Evidence of your original scientific, scholarly, artistic, athletic, or business-related contributions of major significance to the field The applicant created a free software plugin that is popular within their field, and used by teams at well-known companies. The package included install statistics (more than 100k times), and a letter from the CEO of the company that makes the software for which the plugin was written, speaking to its importance. Screenshots from blogs discussing and featuring the plugin were also submitted. Outcome: This criterion received an RFE requesting proof of the plugin’s significance. In response, the applicant submitted a clarifying letter from the same CEO with additonal statistics, as well as six letters from designers at well-known companies attesting to their use of the plugin and its impact. [insert outcome] Evidence of your authorship of scholarly articles in professional or major trade publications or other major media The applicant spoke at a mix of podcast, local, and online events, both individually and as part of a panel. Screenshots of all the event websites were provided along with a letter from a professor of design stating how in this field, speaking at events is considered to be major media on the same level as journal publication. Outcome: This criterion received an RFE requesting (?) Evidence of your performance of a leading or critical role in distinguished organizations The applicant played critical roles in several major projects for his current employer, as well as his past one. Evidence incliudes: a letter from the CEO of his current company, letters from a product manager and design executive from clients of his previous explorer. Outcome: his criterion received an RFE requesting proof that the impact of the applicant’s role on the whole company and how it was beyond the scope of his normal work. The applicant supplied additional letters from senior executives addressing these questions. The applicant also challenged the necessity to demonstrate the criteria. Evidence that you command a high salary or other significantly high remuneration in relation to others in the field The applicant makes $230k a year, which is x% above the median for designers in the united states, demonstrated through sceenshots of salary data from glassdoor (?) and the applicant’s paystubs (?). Outcome: This criterion received an RFE for the applicant’s W2s. [insert outcome here] Timeline Get supporting letters The applicant builds evidence and gets support letter demonstrating how they meet at least three of the ten EB1 criteria Typically takes: 2–4 months Outcome: Applicant has strong evidence and support letters. Submit application (I-140) Evidence and supporting letters are mailed into USCIS, along with a filled out form I-140. This is the official greencard application. Approval time: 3-6 months(?). Applicants can pay $1,500 for a 15 day response. This is called premium processing. Outcome: Greencard application is either accepted, RFE’ed or rejected Respond to RFE (optional) If your application receives a request for evidence, you have three months (?) to brind additional document and/or objections. Approval time: (?). 15 days if premium processing was purchased. Outcome: Greencard application is either accepted or rejected Submit adjustmnet of status (I-485) If an application is accepted and if the applicant’s country’s date of filing (?) is current, the applicant can now file a request to change their status to a permanent resident via form I-485. To get the green card faster, applicants can file the I-485 before their I-140 is accepted, with the risk of wasting money and effort should the latter be rejected. Approval time: Depends on which USCIS service center you applied with Outcome: Receive greencard. Apply for travel document and employment authorization (I-131 and I-765) Because it can take a long time for an ajustment of status to get approved, people usually concurrently apply for travel docuemnt and employment authorization at the same time. These documents are faster to get, and when combined together, provide almost all the benefits of holding a greencard. Approval time: Depends on which USCIS service center you applied with Outcome: Be able to travel freely and work for whoever you want Advice Generally it is better to put on a strong showing for fewer (typically four or five) criteria, than trying to do more but less well. If you have a previously accepted I-140 from a lower preference (EB2 or EB3), you can use that date to accelerate your EB1 if your country is not current. It really helps to have access to famous people: senior executives, well-known professionals in your field, professors, public figures, etc. Cultivate these relationships early. If you don’t already clearly meet these criteria, plan for one to two years to go meet them. Get your letters on official letterhead, even if it’s not technically required. It can be a cause of RFE. In a pinch a “personal” letterhead could do. If your EB1 is approved, this means you’re almost guaranteed to also get approved for the O1 visa, which can be convenient if you need to work in the US while your greencard is processing. For people who are very likely to agree to signing a lettr, it is better to pre-write the lettter for them before you even ask if they want to do it. This way, you can immediately give them something to sign once they agree, saving yourself the back and forth from your lead going cold while your legal team works on the letter. You’ll be getting a lot of letters, so this adds up. On non-immigrant visas like the TN, it is inadvisable to leave the country from the day you submit your application until you get your travel authorization, even if your application is accepted. This could last anywhere from 6–8 months. You should plan ahead for this. The country of the greencard applicant is not based on their citizenship, but place of birth. A British citizen born in India is Indian from this perspective. Spouses also get a greencard if you file together (?) When challenging an RFE, it is best to also respond to the request, even if unreasonable, as a show of good faith.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EB3 greecard deepdive</title><link href="/2020/02/25/EB3-deepdive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EB3 greecard deepdive" /><published>2020-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2020/02/25/EB3-deepdive</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/02/25/EB3-deepdive.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often known simply as the employment or third preference greencard, this is the standard option for anyone seeking permanent residency. To get this, the applicant must have a petitioning employer demonstrate that this person is well-paid, and that their permanent presence in the US will not come at the detriment of American labor. This option requires the least effort from the applicant, but as a result ties them to their employer for the duration of the application, which can take up to three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This option is best for professionals from country where there is no wait time to get a greencard, and who plan on staying with their current employer for at least three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;labour-certification-step-1-of-perm-or-pwd&quot;&gt;Labour certification (step 1 of PERM or PWD)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employer files a prevailing wage requestion or PWD to determine your pay/salary, based on where your job is located and the current economic environment. When the PWD is received, the company has 90 days to file. This typically takes 2–3 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recruitment-step-2-of-perm-or-eta-9089&quot;&gt;Recruitment (step 2 of PERM or ETA 9089)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employer goes through an extensive recruitment process for 90-120 days (60 days min) to prove that they can’t find a person who can fill this role. At the end of this process, they prepare a document called a recruitment report to tell the story of how this will not take away an american job. Once recruitment is complete, employer files an ETA-9089 form. If all goes well, the DOL will issue a permanent labor certification in response&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;audit-optional&quot;&gt;Audit (optional)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apply-for-greencard-i-140&quot;&gt;Apply for greencard (I-140)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adjustment-of-status&quot;&gt;Adjustment of status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-greencard&quot;&gt;Get greencard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;advice&quot;&gt;Advice&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">TL;DR Often known simply as the employment or third preference greencard, this is the standard option for anyone seeking permanent residency. To get this, the applicant must have a petitioning employer demonstrate that this person is well-paid, and that their permanent presence in the US will not come at the detriment of American labor. This option requires the least effort from the applicant, but as a result ties them to their employer for the duration of the application, which can take up to three years. This option is best for professionals from country where there is no wait time to get a greencard, and who plan on staying with their current employer for at least three years. Timeline Labour certification (step 1 of PERM or PWD) Employer files a prevailing wage requestion or PWD to determine your pay/salary, based on where your job is located and the current economic environment. When the PWD is received, the company has 90 days to file. This typically takes 2–3 months. Recruitment (step 2 of PERM or ETA 9089) Employer goes through an extensive recruitment process for 90-120 days (60 days min) to prove that they can’t find a person who can fill this role. At the end of this process, they prepare a document called a recruitment report to tell the story of how this will not take away an american job. Once recruitment is complete, employer files an ETA-9089 form. If all goes well, the DOL will issue a permanent labor certification in response Audit (optional) Apply for greencard (I-140) Adjustment of status Get greencard Advice</summary></entry></feed>